颠峰时期的罗马帝国非常庞大
领土由非洲沙漠伸延至...
英国北部边境
全球超过四份一人口活于...
凯撒王朝的统治下
在公元180年的冬天 奥利里亚斯大帝...
跟日耳曼外族维持了12年的战争...
正接近尾声
只差最后一个据点 罗马人便能取得胜利...
并把和平带给整个帝国
日耳曼
长官
Sir.
将军
General.
长官
Sir.
又瘦又饿
Lean and hungry.
-还没有消息? -没有
-Still nothing? -Not a sign.
-他去了多久? -接近两小时了
-How long has he been gone? -Nearly two hours.
他们会迎战吗?
Will they fight, sir?
很快便会知道
We shall know soon enough.
士兵  我命令了你把弩炮推向前
Soldier, I ordered you to move those catapults forward.
-射程未够远 -距离远一点也好
-They're out of range. -Range is good.
-对骑兵的威胁... -可以接受  同意吧?
-The danger to the cavalry... -Is acceptable. Agreed?
他们说不
They say no.
人们应该清楚当自己被征服了
People should know when they're conquered.
你会吗  昆特斯?
Would you, Quintus?
我会吗?
Would I?
-力量与荣耀  -力量与荣耀
-Strength and honor. -Strength and honor.
我发出指示  便开始进攻
At my signal, unleash hell.
装弩炮弹
Load the catapults.
步兵列阵准备前进
Infantry form up for advance.
-弓箭手准备好 -弓箭手!
-Archers ready. -Archers!
-搭箭!  搭箭!
-Nock! -Nock!
兄弟们!
Fratres!
-麦克西马!  -麦克西马!
-Maximus! -Maximus!
三星期后  我会收割我的农作物
Three weeks from now, I will be harvesting my crops.
想像你会在哪里  便会实现
Imagine where you will be, and it will be so.
保持阵线!  跟着我!
Hold the line! Stay with me!
如果你发现得自己一个人
If you find yourself alone,
骑行于绿野  阳光洒在脸上
riding in green fields with the sun on your face,
不用苦恼
do not be troubled.
因为你已到了极乐世界 已经死了!
For you are in Elysium, and you're already dead!
兄弟们
Brothers,
我们一生的功业
what we do in life
是永垂不朽的
echoes in eternity.
拉!
Pull!
弩炮准备好了!
Cohorts ready, sir!
弓箭手  点火!
Archers, ignite!
-点火!  -点火!
-Ignite! -Ignite!
弓箭手  拉弓!
Archers, draw!
射!
Loose!
好了  将士们  准备!
All right, men, ready!
保持位置!
Hold the line!
射!
Loose!
装炮!
Reload!
保持位置!
Hold the line!
-拉弓! -射!
-Draw! -Loose!
跟着我!
Stay with me!
罗马胜利!
Roma victor!
普利托里亚十四
你认为他真的快死了?
Do you think he's really dying?
说他快死已说了十年
He's been dying for 10 years.
如果他不是快死了 他不会叫我们去
If he weren't really dying, he wouldn't have sent for us.
或者他只是挂念我们
Maybe he just misses us.
那些参议员呢? 不然他不会召见他们的...
And the senators? He wouldn't have summoned them if...
安静  卡莫德
Peace, Commodus.
在路上两星期
After two weeks on the road,
你不断计算 弄得我头也痛了
your incessant scheming is hurting my head.
他已作了决定 他将会宣布
He's made his decision. He's going to announce it.
他会传位给我
He will name me.
到时我要做的第一件事...
The first thing I shall do when...
就是用竞技向国王陛下致敬
Is honor him with games won'thy of His Majesty.
现在 我要做的第一件事 就是洗个热水澡
For now, the first thing I shall do is have a hot bath.
陛下?
Your Highness?
我们就快到了
We seem to be almost there, sir.
-陛下 -皇上在哪里?
-Sire. -Where's the Emperor?
陛下 他在前面 他们已经去了19天
He's at the front, sire. They've been gone for 19 days.
还不断有伤兵进来
The wounded are still coming in.
拉我的马来
My horse.
陛下
My lord.
吻?
Kiss?
你再次表现了你的英勇 麦克西马
You have proved your valor yet again, Maximus.
让我们盼望  最后一次
Let us hope, for the last time.
没有战斗对手了  陛下
There's no one left to fight, sire.
永远都会有战斗对手
There is always someone left to fight.
我应该怎样奖赏罗马最伟大的将军?
How can I reward Rome's greatest general?
让我回家吧
Let me go home.
回家
Home.
凯撒  他们向你致敬
They honor you, Caesar.
是向你 麦克西马 他们向你致敬
It's for you, Maximus. They honor you.
我错过了吗? 我错过了这战役?
Have I missed it? Have I missed the battle?
你错过了这战争
You have missed the war.
父亲  恭喜你
Father, congratulations.
我会献祭100头公牛 向你的胜利致敬
I shall sacrifice 100 bulls to honor your triumph.
不用浪费公牛
Save the bulls.
向麦克西马致敬吧 是他赢了这战役
Honor Maximus. He won the battle.
-将军 -陛下
-General. -Highness.
罗马向你致敬 而我像兄弟般拥戴你
Rome salutes you, and I embrace you as a brother.
很久了  老朋友
It has been too long, my old friend.
陛下
Highness.
来  父亲  捉着我的手
Here, Father. Take my arm.
是时候我要走了
I think it is time for me to leave.
罗马的光辉也不过这样
So much for the glory of Rome.
很出色的战事
Magnificent battle.
将军  还没死吗?
General. Still alive?
还没死
Still alive.
上天真爱开玩笑
The gods must have a sense of humor.
-上天最眷顾你 -维拉里斯
-The gods must love you. -Valerius.
将军 你回兵营 还是回罗马?
Back to barracks, General? Or to Rome?
回家  见我太太  儿子 还有收成
Home. My wife, my son, the harvest.
真难想像麦克西马做农夫
Maximus the farmer. I still have difficulty imagining that.
昆特斯 污泥比血容易洗掉
You know, dirt cleans off a lot easier than blood, Quintus.
-他在这里 -陛下
-Here he is. -Highness.
佳斯议员  科高议员
Senator Gaius, Senator Falco.
小心佳斯 他会向你花言巧语
Beware of Gaius. He'll pour a honeyed potion in your ear,
然后有天你醒来 只会说"共和国"
and you'll wake up one day and all you'll say is, "Republic, republic, republic."
为什么不? 罗马创建时就是共和国
Well, why not? Rome was founded as a republic.
对  而共和国里 权力在议院手上
Yes, and in a republic the senate has the power.
但佳斯议员当然不会受那影响
But Senator Gaius isn't influenced by that, of course.
你站那一边  将军?  帝皇还是议院?
Where do you stand, General? Emperor or Senate?
士兵的优势
A soldier has the advantage
就是可以看进敌人眼里
of being able to look his enemy in the eye, Senator.
有军队支持 你绝对可以从政
Well, with an army behind you, you could be extremely political.
我警告了你  现在我要救你 失陪了
I warned you. Now I shall save you. Senators.
麦克西马
Maximus.
我需要你这样的能人
I'm going to need good men like you.
我如何为您效劳  陛下?
How may I be of service, Highness?
你是懂得发号令的人
You're a man who knows what it is to command.
你发出命令  他们遵从命令 战事便赢了
You give your orders, the orders are obeyed, and the battle is won.
但这些议员 图谋 争吵 谄媚 欺诈
But these senators scheme, squabble and flatter and deceive.
麦克西马  我们一定要从政客手上拯救罗马
Maximus, we must save Rome from the politicians, my friend.
到时我可以依靠你吗?
Can I count on you when the time comes?
陛下 当你父亲放我走时 我打算回家
Highness, when your father releases me, I intend to return home.
回家?  对  没人比你更有这资格
Home? Well, no one's earned it more.
不要太轻松了 我很快便会找你
Don't get too comfortable. I may call on you before long.
露西娜来了  你知吗?
Lucilla's here. Did you know?
她没有忘记你
She's not forgotten you.
而现在  你是英雄
And now, you're the great man.
如果你是男儿身
If only you had been born a man,
你会是出色的凯撒
what a Caesar you would have made.
父亲
Father.
你会很坚强
You would have been strong.
我想知道  你会是正直的吗?
I wonder, would you have been just?
我会是你教导的一样
I would have been what you taught me to be.
你的旅途怎样?
How was your journey?
很长  不舒服  为什么要我来?
Long. Uncomfortable. Why have I come?
我要你帮忙  同你哥哥
I need your help. With your brother.
当然
Of course.
他爱你  一向都是
He loves you. He always has.
而...
And...
现在是他最需要你的时候
he will need you now, more than ever.
不说政治了
Enough of politics.
让我们假装你是个忠诚的女儿
Let us pretend that you are a loving daughter,
而我是个好父亲
and I am a good father.
这是很好的假定  不是吗?
This is a pleasant fiction, isn't it?
早安
Good morning to you.
我需要多三匹马
I need three more horses.
一!  二!  三!
One! Two! Three!
四!
Four!
一!  二!
One! Two!
你召见我  凯撒?
You sent for me, Caesar?
-凯撒? -再告诉我  麦克西马
-Caesar? -Tell me again, Maximus.
我们在这里做什么?
Why are we here?
为了罗马的荣耀  陛下
For the glory of the empire, sire.
是的
Yes.
对  我记起了
Yes, I remember.
你看见那地图吗?
Do you see that map, Maximus?
那是我创造了的世界
That is the world which I created.
25年了
For 25 years,
我侵略  杀人  扩张帝国
I have conquered, spilt blood, expanded the empire.
我做凯撒以来 只有四年没有战争
Since I became Caesar, I've known four years without war.
20年里只有四年和平
Four years of peace in 20.
为了什么?
And for what?
我只带了剑  没有其他
I brought the sword. Nothing more.
凯撒  你一生...
Caesar, your life...
请不要那样称呼我
Please. Please don't call me that.
来  请
Come. Please.
来坐下
Come sit.
现在让我们谈谈
Let us talk together now,
简单的男人对话
very simply, as men.
麦克西马
Well, Maximus,
说吧
talk.
我有五千个手下在冰冻的泥里
Five thousand of my men are out there in the freezing mud.
当中有三千个重伤和流血
Three thousand of them are bloodied and cleaved.
有二千个永不会离开这里
Two thousand will never leave this place.
我不会相信他们的战斗和死亡 是没有意义的
I will not believe that they fought and died for nothing.
那你会相信什么?
And what would you believe?
他们为了你和罗马而战
They fought for you and for Rome.
罗马是什么?
And what is Rome, Maximus?
我见过很多世界上其他的地方
I've seen much of the rest of the world.
很残暴和黑暗  罗马是曙光
It is brutal and cruel and dark. Rome is the light.
但你未去过罗马
Yet you have never been there.
你没见过它变成怎样
You have not seen what it has become.
我快死了
I am dying, Maximus.
当一个人看见自己的尽头
When a man sees his end,
他希望知道他是活得有意义的
he wants to know there was some purpose to his life.
世人将来会怎样评论我?
How will the world speak my name in years to come?
我会被认为是哲学家?
Will I be known as the philosopher?
斗士?
The warrior?
暴君?
The tyrant?
还是让罗马重现真本性的皇帝?
Or will I be the Emperor who gave Rome back her true self?
曾经有一个罗马梦
There was once a dream that was Rome.
你只能低声说
You could only whisper it.
太大声了它便会消失
Anything more than a whisper and it would vanish,
它非常脆弱
it was so fragile.
我恐怕它捱不过冬天
And I fear that it will not survive the winter.
麦克西马
Maximus,
让我们低声说
let us whisper now,
你和我
together, you and I.
你有个儿子
You have a son.
说说你的家
Tell me about your home.
我的屋在特鲁希略的山上
My house is in the hills above Trujillo.
一个很简单的地方
A very simple place.
阳光温了粉红色石头
Pink stones that warm in the sun.
厨房花园日间有香草气味
A kitchen garden that smells of herbs in the day,
晚上则有茉莉香
jasmine in the evening.
通过闸门是一棵巨大的杨树
Through the gate is a giant poplar.
无花果  苹果  啤梨
Figs, apples, pears.
泥土是黑色的 就像我太太的头发一样黑
The soil, Marcus, black. Black like my wife's hair.
南面斜坡是葡萄 北面是橄榄
Grapes on the south slopes, olives on the north.
野马在我家附近玩 它们会逗我儿子
Wild ponies play near my house. They tease my son.
他想做它们一份子
He wants to be one of them.
你上一次在家是何时?
When was the last time you were home?
2年零264天  再加上今早
Two years, 264 days and this morning.
我妒忌你  麦克西马 那是很好的家
I envy you, Maximus. It's a good home.
值得为它奋斗
Worth fighting for.
还有一项职责...
There is one more duty...
我要在你回家前交给你
that I ask of you before you go home.
你要我做什么  凯撒?
What would you have me do, Caesar?
我要你在我死后 做罗马的保护者
I want you to become the protector of Rome after I die.
我会为了一个目标赐你权力
I will empower you to one end alone,
就是把权力还给罗马的人民
to give power back to the people of Rome,
和终止使罗马残破的腐败
and end the corruption that has crippled it.
你会接受我给你的这份光荣吗?
Will you accept this great honor that I have offered you?
绝对不愿意
With all my heart, no.
麦克西马
Maximus,
那正是为什么要你
that is why it must be you.
但应该找个长官  议员
But surely a prefect, a senator,
认识那城市和她政治的人
somebody who knows the city, who understands her politics.
但你没有被她的政治腐化
But you have not been corrupted by her politics.
-那卡莫德呢? -卡莫德不是有道德的人
-And Commodus? -Commodus is not a moral man.
你年轻时便已知道这点
You have known that since you were young.
卡莫德不能统治
Commodus cannot rule.
一定不能让他统治
He must not rule.
你是我应该有的儿子
You are the son that I should have had.
卡莫德会接受我这决定
Commodus will accept my decision.
他知道军队忠于你
He knows that you command the loyalty of the army.
我需要时间考虑
I need some time, sire.
好的
Yes.
日落前  希望你会同意
By sunset, I hope you will have agreed.
来像我儿子般拥抱我
Now embrace me as my son.
和给我这老人拿多张被来
And bring an old man another blanket.
-现在我父亲偏袒你 -公主殿下
-My father favors you now. -My lady.
-已前不是这样 -很多东西已变了
-It was not always so. -Many things change.
很多东西  但不是全部
Many things. Not everything.
麦克西马  等等
Maximus, stop.
让我看你的脸
Let me see your face.
-你好像不高兴 -我损失了很多手下
-You seem upset. -I lost many men.
我父亲要你做什么?
What did my father want with you?
在我回家前祝福我
To wish me well before I leave for home.
你讲大话
You're lying.
我永远知道你在讲大话 因为你讲得很差劲
I could always tell when you were lying, because you were never any good at it.
我并没有得到你信任
I never acquired your comfort with it.
对
True.
但你不需要
But then you never had to.
军人的一生并较简单
Life is more simple for a soldier.
还是你觉得我无情?
Or do you think me heartless?
我觉得你有生存的天份
I think you have a talent for survival.
麦克西马  等等
Maximus, stop.
再见到我真的那么讨厌吗?
Is it really so terrible seeing me again?
不  战斗令我很累
No. I'm tired from battle.
看见我父亲的脆弱令你伤心吧
It hurts you to see my father so fragile.
卡莫德期望父亲会在日内宣布继承人
Commodus expects that my father will announce his succession within days.
你会效力我哥哥 就像效力我父亲一样吗?
Will you serve my brother as you served his father?
我会永远为罗马效力
I will always serve Rome.
你知不知道
Do you know,
我有为你祈祷
I still remember you in my prayers.
是的  我祈祷
Oh, yes. I pray.
我为你丈夫的去世难过 我有哀悼他
I was sad to hear of your husband's death. I mourned him.
-谢谢 -听说你有个儿子
-Thank you. -And I hear you have a son.
是  他叫路西亚斯
Yes. Lucius.
就快八岁了
He'll be nearly eight years old.
我儿子也是就快八岁
My son is also nearly eight.
谢谢你的祝祷
I thank you for your prayers.
我请求祖先的指引
Ancestors, I ask for your guidance.
在天国的母亲 请告知神对我将来的期望
Blessed Mother, come to me with the gods' desire for my future.
在天国的父亲 请用剑保卫我妻子和儿子
Blessed Father, watch over my wife and son with a ready sword.
告诉他们 我生存是为了再次拥抱他们
Whisper to them, I live only to hold them again.
祖先  我尊敬你
Ancestors, I honor you,
并会像你教导我般有尊严地生活
and will try to live with the dignity you have taught me.
西塞罗
Cicero.
先生
Sir.
你不觉得你的工作辛苦吗?
Do you ever find it hard to do your duty?
有时我会做我想做的
Sometimes I do what I want to do.
其余时间  我做我要做的
The rest of the time, I do what I have to.
我们或者最终也未能回家
We may not be able to go home, after all.
你准备好履行对罗马的职责吗?
Are you ready to do your duty for Rome?
是的  父亲
Yes, Father.
你不会是皇帝
You will not be emperor.
哪个更老更有资格的人坐我的位置?
Which wiser, older man is to take my place?
我会把权力传给麦克西马...
My powers will pass to Maximus,
让他掌管着...
to hold in trust,
直至议会适合再次统治
until the Senate is ready to rule once more.
罗马会再次成为共和国
Rome is to be a republic again.
-麦克西马 -是
-Maximus. -Yes.
我的决定令你失望了?
My decision disappoints you?
你曾经写给我...
You wrote to me once,
列出四大美德...
listing the four chief virtues.
智慧...
Wisdom,
正义...
justice,
坚毅...
fortitude,
和克制
and temperance.
我知道我一样也没有
As I read the list, I knew I had none of them.
但父亲  我有其他优点
But I have other virtues, Father.
我有雄心
Ambition.
那会推动我们变得更优胜
That can be a virtue when it drives us to excel.
还有机智  勇敢
Resourcefulness, courage.
或者不是在战场上 但勇敢有很多种
Perhaps not on the battlefield, but there are many forms of courage.
对家族  对你...
Devotion to my family,
的忠诚
to you.
但我的优点不付合你要求
But none of my virtues were on your list.
就像你不想我做你儿子
Even then it was as if you didn't want me for your son.
卡莫德...
Commodus,
你野心太大
you go too far.
我寻找上天的启示...
I searched the faces of the gods
想方法讨好你  令你为我骄傲
for ways to please you, to make you proud.
一句关心的说话...
One kind word,
一个拥抱...
one full hug,
把我拥帖你胸膛...
where you pressed me to your chest and held me tight,
就会像太阳照在我心上一千年
would have been like the sun on my heart for 1,000 years.
我什么令你这么讨厌?
What is it in me you hate so much?
卡莫德
Commodus.
我一直只是想...
All I've ever wanted
达到你的期望  凯撒
was to live up to you, Caesar.
-父亲 -卡莫德...
-Father. -Commodus,
你作为儿子的缺点...
your faults as a son
是我做父亲的失败
is my failure as a father.
过来
Come.
父亲
Father.
我会愿意毁掉全世界...
I would butcher the whole world,
去换你对我的爱!
if you would only have loved me!
麦克西马  皇上要见你 紧急事
Maximus, the Emperor needs you. It's urgent.
跟我一起痛哭  兄弟
Lament with me, brother.
我们的父亲死了
Our great father is dead.
他怎样死的?
How did he die?
医生说没有痛苦
The surgeons say there was no pain.
他睡梦中停止了呼吸
His breath gave out as he slept.
父亲
Father.
你的帝君需要你的忠诚 麦克西马
Your emperor asks for your loyalty, Maximus.
握着我的手
Take my hand.
我只会提出一次
I only offer it once.
昆特斯
Quintus.
凯撒万岁
Hail, Caesar.
我要跟众议员商议
I must talk to the senators. I need their counsel.
-叫醒佳斯和科高 -佳斯和科高
-Wake Gaius and Falco. -Gaius and Falco.
剑
-Sword. -Sword.
麦克西马  谨慎点 那样太鲁莽
Maximus, please be careful. That was not prudent.
鲁莽?皇上被杀害了
Prudent? The Emperor has been slain.
皇上是死于自然
The emperor died of natural causes.
-你为什么拿着兵器  昆特斯? -守卫!
-Why are you armed, Quintus? -Guards!
请不要反抗  麦克西马
Please don't fight, Maximus.
对不起  凯撒下了命令
I'm sorry. Caesar has spoken.
骑至天明...
Ride until dawn,
然后处决他
and then execute him.
昆特斯  看着我 看着我!
Quintus, look at me. Look at me!
答应我你会照顾我家人
Promise me that you will look after my family.
你家人会在死后跟你团聚
Your family will meet you in the afterlife.
跪下
Kneel.
在天国的父亲 请保卫我妻子和儿子
Blessed Father, watch over my wife and son.
告诉他们 我生存是为了再次拥抱他们
Whisper to them that I live only to hold them again.
至少让我死得痛快点
At least give me a clean death.
保留军人的专严
A soldier's death.
结了霜的剑有时会黏着
The frost, sometimes it makes the blade stick.
禁卫军!
Praetorian!
你上一次在家是何时?
When was the last time you were home?
两年零264日和今早
Two years, 264 days and this morning.
在天国的父亲... 保卫我妻子和儿子
Blessed Father, watch over my wife and son with a ready sword.
我会尝试像你教导一样有尊严地生活
I will try to live with the dignity you have taught me.
告诉他们 我生存是为了再次拥抱他们
Whisper to them, I live only to hold them again.
其余皆是尘和空气
...with a ready sword, for all else is dust and air.
告诉他们 我生存是为了再次拥抱他们
Whisper to them, I live only to hold them again.
其余皆是尘和空气
For all else is dust and air.
爸爸!
Papa!
不要死去
Don't die.
你会再见到他们
You'll meet them again.
还未是时候
Not yet.
不要  我们会清理它 忍耐下吧
No. They will clean it. Wait and see.
不要死去
Don't die.
他们会拿你喂狮子
They'll feed you to the lions.
它们比我们值钱
They are won'th more than we are.
好点吧?
Better now?
清洁了  看见吗?
Clean. You see?
苏卡巴-罗马省份
朴森姆!老友
Proximo! My old friend.
你在这里的每天都是好日子
Every day is a great day when you are here,
但今天是你最幸运的一天
but today is your most fortunate day.
你卖给我的长颈鹿不肯交配
Those giraffes you sold me, they won't mate.
他们只是走来走去吃东西 不交配
Theyjust walk around eating and not mating.
你把怪长颈鹿卖给我
You sold me queer giraffes.
-快把钱退还给我 -不可能
-I want my money back. -Not a chance.
-我给你好价钱 -什么货?
-I do special price for you. -On what?
你见过我的新货未? 过来看看
Have you seen my new stock? Come and see them.
有没有会打架的? 我就快有赛事
Do any of them fight? I've got a match coming up.
有些要来打  有些要来死
Some are good for fighting, others for dying.
你大概两样也要
You need both, I think.
起身
Get up.
你做什么行业的?
What's your trade?
我是猎人
I was a hunter.
不  我在迦太基一个盐矿买下他的
No, I bought him from a salt mine in Can'thage.
坐下
Sit down.
军团的标记
Mark of the legion.
罗马国会及人民
-逃兵 -或者是  谁关心?
-Deserter. -Maybe so, but who cares?
是西班牙人
He's a Spaniard.
我买六个  一千元
I'll take six. For 1,000.
一千? 这个努米底亚人已值二千
1,000? The Numidian alone is won'th 2,000.
这些奴隶又残又臭
These slaves are rotten.
那样才更有味道 不  等等!
It all adds to the flavor. No, no, no, wait! Wait!
价钱可以商量
I can negotiate.
我给你二千元 和四千元买野兽
I'll give you 2,000, and 4,000 for the beasts.
友情价是五千元
That's 5,000 for an old friend.
快!到底要多久才能到我自己的家?
Come on! How long does it take to get into my own house?
我是朴森姆
I am Proximo.
接下来是你悲惨人生的最后数天
I shall be closer to you for the next few days,
而我将会是比你母亲...
which will be the last of your miserable lives,
更亲近的人
than that bitch of a mother that brought you screaming into this world.
我买你不是为了陪伴
I did not pay good money for you for your company.
而是我用你的死亡来赚钱
I paid it so that I could profit from your death.
就像你母亲看着你出生...
And as your mother was there at your beginning,
我会伴着你死亡
so I shall be there at your end.
你将会死  当你死时...
And when you die, and die you shall,
你会转化成这声音...
your transition shall be to the sound of...
斗士们...
Gladiators,
我向你致敬
I salute you.
红色
Red.
黄色
Yellow.
好
Good.
红色
-Red. -Red.
西班牙佬
Spaniard.
暂时够了!
That's enough for the moment!
迟早会到他
His time will come.
下个
Next.
西班牙佬
Spaniard,
你为什么不还手?
why don't you fight?
我们全部都要打
We all have to fight.
我不打的
Well, I don't fight.
我不应在这里 我是作家  我写作...
I shouldn't be here, I'm a scribe, I write down words,
我会说七种语言
and speak seven languages.
那好
Good.
明天你可用七种语言尖叫
Tomorrow, you can scream in seven languages.
或者作家就可以赢取自由
Perhaps the scribe will be the one who wins his freedom.
自由?
Freedom?
我需要做什么?
What do I have to do?
你进竞技场  杀了我
You go in the arena and you kill me.
还有他...
And him,
和这努米底亚人...
and the Numidian,
和这逃兵
and the deserter.
再多100个人
And 100 more.
直到你杀了所有斗士 你便自由了
And when there's no more to fight, you're free.
我做不到
I can't do that.
做不到?
No?
但我做得到
But I can.
那是你守护神的标记?
Is that the sign of your gods?
那样不会触怒他们吗?
Will that not anger them?
天神特别眷顾你
The gods favor you.
红是天神的颜色
Red is the gods' color.
今天你会需要他们帮助
You will need their help today.
朴森姆!
Proximo!
还是那德国人领先?
Still leading with the German?
群众喜欢野蛮人
The crowd love a barbarian.
而且他令我富有
Besides that, he's making me rich.
那努米底亚人落过场未?
Has that Numidian fought before?
未  第一次
No, first time.
那个  是苦力  士兵?
And that one, laborer, soldier?
他是西班牙人
He's a Spaniard.
在场上像个废人一样
He might as well be a eunuch for what he brings to the ring.
五百元买努米底亚人 和西班牙人那队会过关
500 sestertii, the Numidian and Spaniard team makes it through.
一千元  如果努米底亚人独自过关
And 1,000, that the Numidian makes it through alone.
你要我买自己的人输?
Are you asking me to bet against my own man?
那是不道德的
It's unethical.
如果我加到二千元呢?
What if I make it 2,000?
你们有些在想你不会搏斗
Some of you are thinking you won't fight,
有些觉得你不能搏斗
some that you can't fight.
他们全部都这样说 直到站在场中
They all say that until they're out there.
听
Listen.
杀!
-Kill! Kill! Kill! -Kill! Kill! Kill!
把这个插进另一个人的血肉里...
Thrust this into another mars flesh,
他们就会欢呼和拥戴你
and they will applaud and love you for that.
而你...
And you,
你会开始因为那样...
you may begin to love them
而喜欢他们
for that.
最终我们都要死
Ultimately, we're all dead men.
悲哀的是我们不能选择怎样死
Sadly, we cannot choose how,
但我们可以决定怎样去到那一刻...
but we can decide how we meet that end,
而令别人记得...
in order that we are remembered
我们
as men.
快!
Come on!
左面的  拔盾!
On the left, draw your shields!
右面的  拔剑!
On the right, draw your swords!
杀!杀!
-Kill! Kill! Kill! -Kill! Kill! Kill!
红跟黄两个一队
Pair them up, red with yellow.
下个!
Next!
打!
Move!
夺权者!
Usurper!
罗马国会及人民
-走! -我们不要你统治  卡莫德!
-Go away! -You'll never rule us, Commodus!
他像个胜利英雄般进城 但他胜了什么?
He enters Rome like a conquering hero. But what has he conquered?
格勒斯  给他一点时间吧 他还年轻
Give him time, Gracchus. He's young.
我觉得他可以做得很好
I think he could do very well.
为了罗马  还是为了你?
For Rome, or for you?
路西亚斯  去你母亲处 她会欢喜的
Go to your mother, Lucius. It's what she'd like.
-路西亚斯! -妈妈!
-Lucius! -Mother!
凯撒万岁
Hail, Caesar.
参议员
Senators.
罗马迎接她的新皇帝
Rome greets her new emperor.
你忠心的臣民欢迎你  陛下
Your loyal subjects bid you welcome, Highness.
谢谢  科高
Thank you, Falco.
至于忠心的臣民 希望不是太昂贵
And for the loyal subjects, I trust they werert too expensive.
-凯撒 -格勒斯
-Caesar. -Gracchus.
凯撒  全罗马因你的回来而喜悦
All Rome rejoices in your return, Caesar.
有很多事情需要你处理
But there are many matters that require your attention.
请肃静
To order, please. To order.
凯撒  为了请你指引
For your guidance, Caesar,
议会准备了一系列草案...
the Senate has prepared a series of protocols...
去开始处理市内的很多问题
to begin addressing the many problems in the city,
首先是希腊区的基本卫生...
beginning with basic sanitation for the Greek Quarter,
要对抗已在那里滋生的瘟疫
to combat the plague which is already springing up there.
所以  如果凯撒...
So, if Caesar...
你明白吗  格勒斯?
Don't you see, Gracchus?
这就是问题所在  不是吗?
That's the very problem, isn't it?
我父亲用所有时间...
My father spent all his time at study,
去钻研学术及哲理的书籍
at books of learning and philosophy.
他临终时还在审阅 议会的奏书
He spent his twilight hours reading scrolls from the Senate.
而却一直忘记了人民
And all the while, the people were forgotten.
但陛下  议会就是人民
But the senate is the people, sire,
从人民选出为人民说话
chosen from among the people to speak for the people.
我相信没多少人像你吃得那样好 格勒斯
I doubt many of the people eat so well as you do, Gracchus.
或有那么多美丽的女人  佳斯
Or have such splendid mistresses, Gaius.
我明白我的人民
I think I understand my own people.
那或者凯撒可以用他丰富的经验...
Then perhaps Caesar will be so good as to teach us,
来教我们
out of his own extensive experience.
我称之为爱
I call it love.
我是人民的父亲 他们是我孩子
I am their father. The people are my children.
我要紧紧拥抱他们
And I shall hold them to my bosom and embrace them tightly.
陛下  你试过拥抱死于瘟疫的人吗?
Have you ever embraced someone dying of plague, sire?
没有  但你再打断我的话...
No, but if you interrupt me again,
我会要你那样做
I assure you that you shall.
议员  我哥哥很累了
Senator, my brother is very tired.
把议程给我吧 凯撒会做到所有罗马需要的
Leave your list with me. Caesar shall do all that Rome requires.
公主陛下 你永远轻轻一句便使我们服从
My lady, as always, your lightest touch commands obedience.
他们有什么资格教训我?
Who are they to lecture me?
卡莫德  议会是有其作用的
Commodus, the Senate has its uses.
有什么用?他们只是空谈
What uses? All they do is talk.
应该只是你和我统治罗马
It should be just you and me and Rome.
想也不要想 议会一直存在
Don't even think it. There's always been a Senate.
罗马变了
Rome has changed.
需要一个皇帝去统治帝国
It takes an emperor to rule an empire.
当然  但要让人民保留...
Of course, but leave the people their...
假象?
Illusions?
传统
Traditions.
我父亲和外族的战争...
My father's war against the barbarians.
他自己说的  没有达到什么 但人民爱戴他
He said it himself, it achieved nothing. But the people loved him.
人民永远热爱胜利
The people always love victories.
为什么?他们没有看到战事
Why? They didn't see the battles.
日耳曼关他们什么事?
What do they care about Germania?
他们想看见罗马的伟大
They care about the greatness of Rome.
"罗马的伟大"
"The greatness of Rome."
那是什么?
Well, what is that?
伟大是一个概念
It's an idea. Greatness.
-伟大是一个理想 -正是  一个理想
-Greatness is a vision. -Exactly. A vision.
你明吗  露西娜?
Do you not see, Lucilla?
我会给罗马人民一个理想 他们会因此爱戴我
I will give the people a vision of Rome, and they'll love me for it.
而他们很快便会忘记 几个老人沉闷的训导
And they'll soon forget the tedious sermonizing of a few dry old men.
我会给人民 他们一生中最大的理想
I will give the people the greatest vision of their lives.
斗士-暴力
有好喝的红酒和白酒!
White and red wine for your drinking pleasure!
竞技
Games.
150天的竞技
One hundred and fifty days of games.
他比我想像中聪明
He's cleverer than I thought.
聪明  如果不是怕了他的禁卫军...
Clever. The whole of Rome would be laughing at him,
全罗马都会耻笑他
if they werert so afraid of his Praetorians.
恐惧和好奇  很有效的组合
Fear and wonder. A powerful combination.
你以为人民真会被这个诱惑吗?
You really think the people are going to be seduced by that?
我觉得他知道罗马是什么 罗马就是群众
I think he knows what Rome is. Rome is the mob.
变些戏法便能迷惑他们
Conjure magic for them, and they'll be distracted.
拿走他们的自由 他们依然会大笑
Take away their freedom, and still they'll roar.
罗马的心脏不是议会殿
The beating heart of Rome is not the marble of the Senate.
而是斗兽场
It's the sand of the Colosseum.
他会带给他们死亡...
He'll bring them death,
而他们会因此爱戴他
and they will love him for it.
你只需杀  杀  杀
All you do is kill, kill, kill.
群众不是要屠夫 他们要英雄
The crowd don't want a butcher, they want a hero.
我们要他们不断回来看
We want them to keep coming back.
所以不要只顾把他们斩件 记着你是要娱乐观众
So don'tjust hack them to pieces, remember you are an entertainer.
西班牙人
Spaniard.
快去娱乐他们!
So entertain!
那是娱乐吧?
Are you not entertained? Are you not entertained?
你们来不是为了这个吗?
Is this not why you're here?
西班牙人! 西班牙人! 西班牙人!
Spaniard! Spaniard! Spaniard!
你想要什么?
What do you want?
女人?
Girl?
男人?
Boy?
-是你叫我来的 -是
-You sent for me. -Yes, I did.
你很好  但不够
You're good, Spaniard, but you're not that good.
你可以很出色
You could be magnificent.
需要杀人  所以我去杀 那就够了
I'm required to kill, so I kill. That is enough.
对外省区域是够 但不是对罗马
That's enough for the provinces, but not for Rome.
那年轻皇帝安排了一系列表演...
The young emperor has arranged a series of spectacles
去纪念他的父亲奥利里亚斯
to commemorate his father, Marcus Aurelius.
我觉得很有趣...
I find that amusing,
因为当初是奥利里亚斯...
since it was Marcus Aurelius, the wise,
英明博学的奥利里亚斯 禁止了我们
the all-knowing Marcus Aurelius, that closed us down.
终于  在穷乡僻坏捱了五年...
So finally, after five years of scratching a living
艰苦的生活后
in flea-infested villages,
我们终于可以回去 我们所属的地方...
we're finally going back to where we belong.
斗兽场
The Colosseum.
你应去见识斗兽场
You should see the Colosseum, Spaniard.
五万罗马人...
Fifty thousand Romans,
看着你挥剑的每一个动作
watching every movement of your sword,
渴望你斩杀对手
willing you to make that killer blow.
你挥击前的静默 与之后的狂呼
The silence before you strike and the noise afterwards.
群情不断高涨...
It rises. It rises up,
似风暴一样
like a storm.
就像你是雷雨神
As if you were the thunder god himself.
-你曾经是斗士? -是的
-You were a gladiator? -Yes, I was.
你赢取了自由?
You won your freedom?
很久以前  皇帝...
A long time ago, the Emperor
赐了我一把木剑
presented me with a rudius.
那只是一把木剑
It's just a wooden sword.
象征了你的自由
The symbol of your freedom.
他碰了我的肩膊 我便自由了
He touched me on the shoulder, and I was free.
你认识奥利里亚斯?
You knew Marcus Aurelius?
我没说我认识他 我说他碰了我的肩膊一下
I did not say I knew him. I said he touched me on the shoulder once.
你问我要什么
You asked me what I want.
我亦要站在皇帝面前...
I, too, want to stand in front of the Emperor,
就像你一样
as you did.
那听我说  跟我学习
Then listen to me. Learn from me.
我是最好的 不是因为我杀得快
I wasrt the best because I killed quickly.
而是因为观众喜欢我
I was the best because the crowd loved me.
赢取观众的心  你便会赢得自由
Win the crowd, and you'll win your freedom.
我会赢到观众的心
I will win the crowd.
我会让他们看到从未看过的
I will give them something they've never seen before.
那我们应该一起去罗马...
So, Spaniard, we shall go to Rome together
去进行血腥的历险
and have bloody adventures.
那些妓女会喂哺我们...
And the great whore will suckle us
直到我们又胖又开心 吃不下为止
until we are fat and happy and can suckle no more.
然后...
And then,
够多人死了后
when enough men have died,
或者你会重获自由
perhaps you will have your freedom.
来  用这个
Here. Use this.
我的国家在那里某处
It's somewhere out there, my country.
我的家
My home.
我妻子在准备食物
My wife is preparing food.
我的女儿们从河里打水
My daughters carry water from the river.
我会再见到她们吗?
Will I ever see them again?
大概不会
I think, no.
你相信你死后会见到她们吗?
Do you believe you'll see them again when you die?
我相信
I think so.
但我很快便会死
But then, I will die soon.
而她们要过很多年才死
They will not die for many years.
我要等
I'll have to wait.
但你会等?
But you would? Wait?
当然
Of course.
你知吗...
You see,
我妻子和儿子...
my wife and my son
已经在等我
are already waiting for me.
你会见到他们  但没那么快
You'll meet them again. But not yet.
没那么快
Not yet.
-除非... -没那么快
-Unless... -Not yet.
没那么快
Not yet.
他在那里
There he is.
出去
Out.
快行  出去!
Move, go, out!
再见到你真好  老友
Good to see you again, old friend.
请带给我幸运
Bring me fortune.
你有没见过像这样的东西?
Have you ever seen anything like that before?
我不知道人可以建造出来
I didn't know men could build such things.
赢取群众的心
Win the crowd.
进去  快
Get inside. Move.
进去
Inside.
他睡得那样好因为有人爱他
He sleeps so well because he's loved.
来  哥哥  很夜了
Come, brother. It's late.
我会令罗马成为历代神话
I will make Rome the wonder of the ages.
那是格勒斯和他的朋友们 不会明白的
That is what Gracchus and his friends don't understand.
我的所有欲望正在把我撕裂
All my desires are splitting my head to pieces.
卡莫德  喝这药剂
Commodus, drink this tonic.
我觉得时候差不多了
I think the time is almost right.
我可以在纪念父亲的庆祝会上...
I could announce the dissolution of the Senate
宣布解散国会
at the celebration to honor our father.
你认为我应该吗?
Do you think I should?
人民准备好没有?
Are the people ready?
我觉得你现在需要休息
I think you need your rest now.
你会陪着我吗?
Will you stay with me?
依然怕黑吗  哥哥?
Still afraid of the dark, brother?
依然
Still.
永远
Always.
-今晚陪我 -你知我不会
-Stay with me tonight. -You know I won't.
那吻我
Then kiss me.
睡吧
Sleep, brother.
有又聋又哑的仆人...
Having servants who are deaf and mute
至少让我活得久一点
at least ensures I live a little longer.
他们在拘捕学者
They're arresting scholars now.
任何敢表达意见的 甚至包括作者和史记者
Anyone who dare speak out. Even satirists and chroniclers.
还有数学家
And mathematicians.
全部喂斗兽场
And all to feed the arena.
国会没有通过战争法例
The Senate did not approve martial law.
这全是禁卫军的恐怖势力
This reign of terror is entirely the Praetorians.
我入黑后不敢外出
I'm afraid to go out after dark.
你更应担心日间的活动
You should be more afraid of your activities during the day.
国会中布满他的线眼 由那好色的科高带领
The Senate is full of his spies, led by that whore master, Falco.
究竟他在想什么? 那是最令我困惑的
But what is in his mind? That's what I trouble myselfwith.
他整天只顾...
He spends all his days singularly obsessed,
筹划你父亲的纪念庆典
planning the festival to honor your father.
他连政府最基本的工作也忽略
He neglects even the most fundamental task of government.
他到底在计划什么?
So just what is he planning?
用什么来支付?
And what pays for it?
每天这些竞技支出庞大 但我们没加新税项
These daily games are costing a fortune, yet we have no new taxes.
未来
The future.
用未来支付
The future pays for it.
他已开始卖谷物贮备
He's started selling the grain reserves.
不是吧
This can't be true.
他在卖罗马贮备的谷物
He's selling Rome's reserves of grain.
人民在两年后便会捱饿
The people will be starving in two years.
希望他们享受...
I hope they're enjoying the games,
那些竞技 因为不久他们便会因此而灭亡
because soon enough they'll be dead because of them.
-罗马人要知道真相 -怎样?
-Rome must know this. -And how?
他打算解散国会
He's going to dissolve the Senate.
谁会及时告诉他们? 你  格勒斯?
And who will tell them before it's too late? You, Gracchus?
你  佳斯
You, Gaius.
你会否在国会上指责我哥哥?
Will you make a speech on the floor of the Senate,denouncing my brother?
然后看着你全家被推进斗兽场?
And then see your family in the Colosseum?
谁敢?
Who'd dare?
我每天都活在恐惧中...
I have been living in a prison of fear every day,
因为我儿子是皇位继承人
because my son is heir to the throne.
他一定要死
He must die.
但昆特斯和禁卫军会夺去控制权
Quintus and the Praetorians would simply seize control for themselves.
不  把蛇头斩了 便不能袭击人
No. Cut off the head and the snake cannot strike.
露西娜  佳斯说得对
Lucilla, Gaius is right.
不能压制禁卫军的话 我们不会成功
Until we can neutralize the Praetorians, we can achieve nothing.
那我们坐以待毙?
So we do nothing?
不  我们在暗中计划
No, child. We keep our counsel.
我们准备
We prepare.
人民支持他 我们的声音便没有力量
As long as the people support him, we are voices without steel.
我们是空气
We are air.
但每天他都在竖敌
But with every day that passes, he makes enemies.
终有一天  他的敌人会多过朋友
One day, he'll have more enemies than friends.
那就是我们行动的时候
And on that day, we will act.
那时我们便反击
Then we will strike.
在那刻来临前...
But until then,
我们是听话的
we are docile.
我们是服从的
We are obedient.
而我们亦是不忠的
And we are treacherous.
快!
Come on!
好了  够了
All right, that's enough.
皇帝要战争
The Emperor wants battles,
而我不想牺牲我最好的战士
and I don't want to sacrifice my best fighters.
观众想看战争 所以皇帝给他们看
The crowd wants battles, so the Emperor gives them battles.
-你已有迦太基之役 -是迦太基大屠杀
-You get the battle of Can'thage. -Massacre of Can'thage.
那你为什么不去监狱
Well, why don't you go down to the prison,
抓乞丐和盗贼?
round up all the beggars and thieves?
我们做了
We've done that.
如果你想要全帝国最好的斗士
If you want to give away the best gladiators in the whole of the empire,
我要双倍价钱
then I want double the rates.
你不接受合约价钱 我们就取消合约
You'll get your contract rates, or you'll get your contract canceled.
不满意吗?
You don't like it?
那爬回去你出来的屎洞吧
Then you can crawl back down that shit hole that you came from.
卡西亚  求你 你可以放了我们
Cassius, please. You can free us.
你是不是那个 他们叫西班牙人的斗士?
Gladiator, are you the one they call the Spaniard?
是的
Yes.
他们说你是巨人
They said you were a giant.
他们说你能单手 握碎一个男人的头骨
They said you could crush a mars skull with one hand.
男人?  不能
A mars? No.
男孩吧
A boy's.
-西班牙有好马匹吗? -其中最好的
-Do they have good horses in Spain? -Some of the best.
这是亚尊图  这是史加图
This is Argento and this is Scan'to.
它们是我的马
They were my horses.
它们被带走了
They were taken from me.
我喜欢你  我会为你打气
I like you, Spaniard. I shall cheer for you.
-他们让你看竞技? -我舅父说那会令我坚强
-They let you watch the games? -My uncle says it makes me strong.
-那你父亲怎样说? -我父亲死了
-And what does your father say? -My father is dead.
路西亚斯主人  时间到了
Master Lucius, it is time.
我要走了
I have to go.
你叫路西亚斯?
Your name is Lucius?
路西亚斯维里斯  以纪念我父亲
Lucius Verus, after my father.
放下!
Lower!
-哥地亚斯! -是?
-Claudius! -Yes?
-多些盾牌!  -好的
-More shields! -All right.
当皇上进场时 高举武器  向他敬礼...
When the Emperor enters, raise your weapons, salute him,
然后齐声说话
and then speak together.
面向皇上 不准背向他
Face the Emperor and don't turn your back on him.
去吧  要死得光荣
Go, and die with honor.
全能的凯撒万岁!
Hail, mighty Caesar!
凯撒!
-Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! -Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
我们将死的向你致敬!
-We who are about to die salute you! -We who are about to die salute you!
今天...
On this day
我们回到神圣的古代
we reach back to hallowed antiquity
重演迦太基的...
to bring you a re-creation of the second fall
第二次失陷!
of mighty Can'thage!
在贫瘠的莎玛平原上
On the barren plain of Zama
站着了异族人汉尼拔...
there stood the invincible armies
的无敌军队
of the barbarian Hannibal.
来自野蛮国家的...
Ferocious mercenaries and warriors
凶残雇佣兵和战士...
from all brute nations,
屈服于无情的毁灭性...
bent on merciless destruction,
征服
conquest.
皇上很高兴献给你们...
Your emperor is pleased to give you
野蛮民族
the barbarian horde!
有没有人当过军?
Anyone here been in the army?
有  我在云度邦拿跟过你
Yes. I served with you at Vindobona.
你可以帮我
You can help me.
不论从闸里走出来的是什么...
Whatever comes out of these gates,
我们要合作才能增加生存机会
we've got a better chance of survival ifwe work together.
你明白吗?
Do you understand?
我们靠在一起  就能生存
Lfwe stay together, we survive.
皇上献给你们 史基比奥的...
The Emperor is pleased to bring you the legionnaires
军团士兵!
of Scipio Africanus!
战死为止!
To the death!
杀!
-Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill! -Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill!
靠紧
Stay close.
聚在一起!
Come together!
靠紧  交替列阵!
Stay close. Staggered columns!
你没有机会
You don't have a chance.
锁紧盾牌  靠在一起
Lock your shields. Stay as one.
靠紧!
Hold!
靠紧一起!
Hold! As one!
做得好
Well done.
靠稳  蹲低!
Hold. Down low!
好!
Yes!
哈根!
Hagen!
这队去战车! 这队跟着我!
This column to the chariot! This column stay with me!
快手!
Quickly!
-出去 -快!
-Get out there. -Hurry!
麦克西马!
Maximus!
单行!
Single column! Single column!
我们胜了!
We win!
我对历史有点模糊  卡西亚...
My history's a little hazy, Cassius,
但那些野蛮人 不是输了迦太基之役吗?
but shouldn't the barbarians lose the battle of Can'thage?
是的  陛下
Yes, sire.
请见谅  陛下
Forgive me, sire.
没关系  我享受惊喜
No, I rather enjoy surprises.
他是谁?
Who is he?
他们叫他做西班牙人  陛下
They call him the Spaniard, sire.
我想会见他
I think I'll meet him.
是  陛下
Yes, sire.
野蛮人万岁!
Hail to the barbarians!
前进!准备武器!
Forward! Arms at ready!
丢低武器
Drop your weapons.
斗士  皇上要见你
Gladiator, the Emperor has asked for you.
我愿为皇上效力
I am at the Emperor's service.
起来
Rise. Rise.
你果然名不虚传  西班牙人
Your fame is well deserved, Spaniard.
你应该是史上最好的斗士
I don't think there's ever been a gladiator to match you.
这小伙子坚说你是赫克托再生
As for this young man, he insists you are Hector reborn.
还是海克力士?
Or was it Hercules?
为什么大英雄不现出真面目 和告知他的真名?
Why doesn't the hero reveal himself and tell us all your real name?
你有名字的吧
You do have a name.
我名字叫斗士
My name is Gladiator.
你竟敢背向我?奴隶!
How dare you show your back to me? Slave!
你立即除下头盔和说出名字
You will remove your helmet and tell me your name.
我名字是麦克西马米里迪亚
My name is Maximus Decimus Meridius,
北军总指挥
commander of the armies of the north,
菲历斯军团的将军
general of the Felix Legions,
真皇帝奥利里亚斯的忠心侍从
loyal servant to the true emperor, Marcus Aurelius,
一个儿子被杀的父亲
father to a murdered son,
一个妻子被杀的丈夫
husband to a murdered wife,
而我会为他们报仇 今世或来世
and I will have my vengeance, in this life or the next.
准备武器!
Arms!
让他活! 活! 活! 活!
Live! Live! Live! Live!
-活! 活! 活! 活!  -活! 活! 活! 活!
-Live! Live! Live! Live! -Live! Live! Live! Live!
放下武器!
Arms, at rest!
-麦克西马! 麦克西马! 麦克西马! -麦克西马! 麦克西马!麦克西马!
-Maximus! Maximus! Maximus! -Maximus! Maximus! Maximus!
父亲
Father.
他为何还活着?
Why is he still alive?
我不知道
I don't know.
他应该死了的
He shouldn't be alive.
那令我气恼
It vexes me.
我非常气恼
I'm terribly vexed.
我一定要那样做
I did what I had to do.
如果照父亲意思 这帝国便会四分五裂了
If Father had had his way, the empire would have been torn apart.
你明白吧
You do see that.
是的
Yes.
你见到他时有什么感觉?
What did you feel when you saw him?
没有感觉
I felt nothing.
他深深的伤害了你  不是吗?
He wounded you deeply, didn't he?
不会多过我伤害他
No more than I wounded him.
他们在日耳曼是骗了我
They lied to me in Germania.
他们说他已经死了
They told me he was dead.
他们骗我  即是不尊重我
If they lie to me, they don't respect me.
他们不尊重我  又怎会爱戴我?
If they don't respect me, how can they ever love me?
那你便要让军团知道...
Then you must let the legions know
他们的叛逆会得到惩罚
their treachery will not go unpunished.
可怜的妹妹
Poor sister.
我不想做你的敌人
I wouldn't want to be your enemy.
你会怎做?
What will you do?
这边
This way.
富有的女士会付高价 给最英勇的斗士
Rich matrons pay well to be pleasured by the bravest champions.
我知道你哥哥会派刺客
I knew your brother would send assassins.
我没想过他会派最好的
I didn't realize he would send his best.
麦克西马  他不知道我来
Maximus, he doesn't know.
我家人活生生被吊和烧死
My family was burnt and crucified while they were still alive.
-我全不知情 -不要骗我!
-I knew nothing... -Don't lie to me!
我为他们哭泣
I wept for them.
就像你为你父亲哭泣?
As you wept for your father? As you wept for your father?
我自那天起便活在恐惧中
I have been living in a prison of fear since that day.
为了对兄长的恐惧 而不能哀悼父亲
To be unable to mourn your father for fear of your brother.
因为儿子是皇位继承人...
To live in terror every moment of every day,
而每一刻都活在恐惧中
because your son is heir to the throne.
我有哭过
I have wept.
我儿子是无辜的
My son was innocent.
我的也是
So is mine.
是否要我儿子死了 你才会信我?
Must my son die, too, before you'll trust me?
我信不信你又有什么关系?
What does it matter if I trust you or not?
上天放过了你 你明白吗?
The gods have spared you. Don't you understand?
今天我看见了一个奴隶 比罗马皇帝更有势力
Today I saw a slave become more powerful than the emperor of Rome.
上天放过了我?
The gods have spared me?
我靠别人怜悯 只有能力娱乐一堆群众
I am at their mercy, with the power only to amuse a mob.
那就是势力
That is power.
群众正是罗马
The mob is Rome.
当卡莫德控制他们 他便控制了所有
And while Commodus controls them, he controls everything.
听我说
Listen to me.
我哥哥有很多敌人 尤其在国会里
My brother has enemies, most of all in the Senate.
但大家都跟随他...
But while the people follow him,
没人敢顶撞他 直至你出现
no one would dare stand up to him until you.
他们反对他  但什么也不做
They oppose him, yet they do nothing.
有些政客把一生奉献给罗马
There are some politicians who have dedicated their lives to Rome.
尤其有一位
One man above all.
如果我安排  你愿意见他吗?
If I can arrange it, will you meet him?
你不明白吗?
Do you not understand?
我可能今晚便死在这里 或明天在场上  我是奴隶!
I may die in this cell tonight, or in the arena tomorrow. I am a slave!
我可以做什么?
What possible difference can I make?
这人跟你想要的一样
This man wants what you want.
那叫他杀了卡莫德!
Then have him kill Commodus!
我曾经认识一个人...
I knew a man once,
他高尚...
a noble man.
有原则  爱我父亲...
A man of principle who loved my father,
而我父亲也爱他
and my father loved him.
他全心为罗马服务
This man served Rome well.
那人不在了
That man is gone.
你哥哥做得很好
Your brother did his work well.
让我帮你
Let me help you.
是  你可以帮我
Yes, you can help me.
忘记你认识过我 永不要再来
Forget you ever knew me, never come here again.
守卫!我们谈完了
Guard! The lady is finished with me.
你叫什么名字?
What's your name?
朱利安克拉苏
Julian Crassus.
名字?
Name?
马可斯  陛下
Marcus, sire.
跟我父亲同名
My father's name.
他们发现那四个尸体时
They must have known of Maximus' escape,
一定知道麦克西马逃走了
when they found the bodies of the four men.
他们以为是野蛮人突袭
They thought it was a barbarian raid.
他们是好人  陛下 他们忠于皇上
These are good men, sire. Loyal to the Emperor.
搭箭!
Load your arrows!
准备放箭!
Prepare to fire!
又或者是你知道...
Then perhaps it was you who knew,
而不告诉我
and never told me.
-我并不知道 -你不知道?
-I didn't know. -You didn't know?
但将军永远有控制权
But a general is always in control.
永远是命令者  不是吗?
Always in command, isn't he?
是的  凯撒
Yes, Caesar.
那下命令吧  快说
Then give the command. Say it.
放箭
Fire.
麦克西马
Maximus.
你指挥过军队? 你打过胜仗?
You commanded legions? You had many victories?
-是的 -在日耳曼?
-Yes. -In Germania?
在很多国家
In many countries.
将军
General.
你有很好的声誉
You have a great name.
他一定要破坏你的声誉才能杀你
He must kill your name before he kills you.
是  在远处
Yes, at the far end.
-佳斯议员 -你好
-Senator Gaius. -Hello.
格勒斯议员
Senator Gracchus.
不常见到你享受这些粗野的群众
Don't often see you enjoying the pleasures of the vulgar crowd.
我不假装是民众的一份子  议员
I don't pretend to be a man of the people, Senator,
但我为人民服务
but I do try to be a man for the people.
凯撒!
-Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! -Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
罗马的人民!
People of Rome!
在安条克的第四天...
On the fourth day ofAntioch,
我们庆祝这竞技赛的第64天
we can celebrate the 64th day of the games.
伟大仁慈的...
And in his majestic charity,
皇上今天赐予罗马人民...
the Emperor has deigned this day to favor the people of Rome
一个历史性的最后一场竞技
with an historical final match.
退了休五年 今天重回斗兽场
Returning to the Colosseum today, after five years in retirement,
凯撒献给你们...
Caesar is pleased to bring you
在罗马史上唯一不败的...
the only undefeated champion
斗士
in Roman history,
传奇的底格里斯!
the legendary Tigris of Gaul!
他太懂得煽动群众
He knows too well how to manipulate the mob.
奥利里亚斯有个梦想的罗马  朴森姆
Marcus Aurelius had a dream that was Rome, Proximo.
这个不是
This is not it. This is not it!
奥利里亚斯死了  麦克西马
Marcus Aurelius is dead, Maximus.
我们这些人只是尘与影
We mortals are but shadows and dust.
尘与影  麦克西马!
Shadows and dust, Maximus!
代表朴森姆训练团...
Representing the training lyceum ofAntonius Proximo,
凯撒献给你...
Caesar is proud to give you
麦克西马!
Aelius Maximus!
他们拥戴他就像他是他们一份子
They embrace him like he's one of their own.
群众是易变的  哥哥 他们一个月后便会忘记他
The mob is fickle, brother. He'll be forgotten in a month.
不  比一个月快很多
No, much sooner than that.
已安排好了
It's been arranged.
我们将死的向你致敬
We who are about to die salute you.
我们支持你  麦克西马!
We're with you, Maximus!
杀了他!
Fight on, finish it!
拉  拉!
Pull, pull!
放!放!
Loose! Loose!
-斩杀他! -杀!
-Gut him! -Kill!
-杀! 杀! 杀! 杀!  -杀! 杀! 杀! 杀!
-Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill! -Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill!
-杀!  -杀!
-Kill! -Kill!
仁慈的麦克西马!
Maximus the Merciful!
麦克西马!
-Maximus! Maximus! Maximus! -Maximus! Maximus! Maximus!
前进  准备武器!
Forward, arms at ready!
我应怎样处置你?
What am I going to do with you?
你总是不死
You simply won't die.
你和我是那样不同吗?
Are we so different, you and I?
你在必要时会杀人  我也是
You take life when you have to, as I do.
我只需要杀多一个人 便完成了
I have only one more life to take. Then it is done.
那现在动手
Then take it now.
他们说你儿子...
They tell me your son
被钉十字架时像女孩般尖叫
squealed like a girl when they nailed him to the cross.
你妻子...
And your wife
像妓女般呻吟...
moaned like a whore
当他们蹂躏她一次又一次...
when they ravaged her again and again
又一次
and again.
你的荣耀很快便会完结
The time for honoring yourself will soon be at an end,
陛下
Highness.
将军!
General! General!
-将军! -西塞罗!
-General! -Cicero!
-将军! -你营地在哪里?
-General! -Where are you camped?
奥斯提亚
Ostia.
-我们爱你  麦克西马! -赞颂胜利者!
-We love you, Maximus! -Praise the victor!
告诉他们将军在生  找我
Tell the men their general lives. Find me.
-继续行! -找我!
-Move along! -Find me!
他们会听见你吗?
Can they hear you?
-谁? -你的家人  在天国
-Who? -Your family, in the afterlife.
-会的 -你跟他们说什么?
-Yes. -What do you say to them?
跟我儿子...
To my boy,
我告诉他我会很快见到他
I tell him I will see him again soon,
还有骑马时脚跟向下
and to keep his heels down when he's riding his horse.
跟我妻子...
To my wife,
不关你事
that is not your business.
现在他们爱戴麦克西马的仁慈
And now they love Maximus for his mercy.
令我不能就这样杀他 不然我看来更残酷
So I can'tjust kill him, or it makes me even more unmerciful.
整件事就像一个恶梦
The whole thing is like some great nightmare.
他在向你挑战
He is defying you.
他每次胜利都是在挑战你
His every victory is an act of defiance.
群众见到  国会也见到
The mob sees this, and so do the Senate.
他每活多一天 他们就更大胆
Every day he lives, they grow bolder.
-杀了他 -不
-Kill him. -No.
我不会让他做烈士
I will not make a martyr of him.
我今天去国会...
When I went to the Senate today,
特意告诉他们 我用了谷物贮备来支付竞技赛
I purposefully told them about using the grain reserves to pay for the games.
你记得发生什么事吗?
And did you note what happened?
-没什么 -对  什么都没发生
-Nothing. -Exactly. Nothing.
一句抗议都没有
Not a single word of protest.
连傲慢的格勒斯议员也没出声
Even the insolent Senator Gracchus was silent as a mouse.
为什么?
Why?
我听说有一种海蛇
I have been told of a certain sea snake
有种特别的方法吸引猎物
which has a very unusual method of attracting its prey.
它会像受了伤一样躺在海底
It will lie at the bottom of the ocean as ifwounded.
然后敌人接近...
Then its enemies will approach,
而它继续躺着不动
and yet it will lie quite still.
然后敌人会一点一点的咬它...
And then its enemies will take little bites of it,
但它依然不动
and yet it remains still.
所以...
So,
我们要不动...
we will lie still,
让敌人来咬
and let our enemies come to us and nibble.
令每个议员也跟着
Have every senator followed.
西赛罗  老友
Cicero, my old friend.
我以为以后再见不到你
I thought perhaps I'd seen you for the last time.
-我以为你死了 -差点
-I thought you were dead. -Close.
士兵们在奥斯提亚多久了?
How long have the men been in Ostia?
整个冬天了
All winter.
-他们看来怎样? -又肥又闷
-And how do they look? -Fat and bored.
-谁在指挥? -某个罗马来的蠢材
-Who's in command? -Some fool from Rome.
你认为他们何时会准备好战斗?
How soon do you think they could be ready to fight?
为了你  明天便行
For you, tomorrow.
我要你为我做一件事
I need you to do something for me.
来  看
Come, see, witness.
如果你未进过场 你可在这里看表演
If you haven't been in the arena, you can see the show here.
巨人麦克西马在击败我们的皇帝卡莫德
Giant Maximus is defeating our emperor, Commodus.
我们怎算? 他在挑战所有人...
What are we to do? He's just defying everyone,
因他挑战他
by doing this to him, they do...
天呀!
My goodness!
-他打中他  他被击败了 -让路!
-He got him, he's defeated. -Give way!
公主陛下? 我在云度邦拿侍奉过你父亲
My lady? I served your father at Vindobona.
-退后 -公主陛下
-Back. -My lady.
我在云度邦拿侍奉过你父亲
I served your father at Vindobona.
退后!
Back!
我还侍奉麦克西马将军 我依然侍奉他
And I served General Maximus. I serve him still.
停下来  停下来
Stop. Stop.
停下来
Stop!
站后
Stand back.
将军叫我传话 他愿意见你那政客
The general sends word, he will meet your politician.
-这是奖励你的忠诚 -谢谢  公主
-For your loyalty, soldier. -Thank you, my lady.
出去吧
Leave us.
格勒斯议员
Senator Gracchus.
将军
General.
希望我今天来已证明了...
I hope my coming here today is evidence enough
你能信任我
that you can trust me.
-议会跟你一致吗? -议会?
-The Senate is with you? -The Senate?
是的  我代表他们
Yes. I can speak for them.
你能还我自由和运我出罗马?
You can buy my freedom and smuggle me out of Rome?
去到哪里?
To what end?
带我出了城墙
Get me outside the city walls.
准备好精壮马匹载我去奥斯提亚 我的军队在那里扎营
Have fresh horses ready to take me to Ostia. My army is encamped there.
第二天的黄昏前 我会带着五千人回来
By nightfall of the second day, I shall return at the head of 5,000 men.
但军团全部有忠于卡莫德的...
But the legions all have new commanders,
新指挥官
loyal to Commodus.
让我的士兵看见我在生 你就会见到他们忠于谁
Let my men see me alive, and you shall see where their loyalties lie.
这太疯狂了
This is madness.
一百年来没有罗马军队进过首都
No Roman army has entered the capital in 100 years.
我不会用一个独裁政权来换另一个!
I will not trade one dictatorship for another!
议员  折衷和空谈的时间过去了
The time for half measures and talk is over, Senator.
那你完成了辉煌的政变后  又怎样?
And after your glorious coup, what then?
你会带你的五千战士离去?
You'll take your 5,000 warriors and leave?
我会离开
I will leave.
士兵会留下保护你们
The soldiers will stay for your protection,
听命于议会
under the command of the Senate.
那...
So,
罗马到了你手上 你会就这样把它还给人民?
once all of Rome is yours, you'll just give it back to the people?
告诉我为什么
Tell me why.
因为那是一个人的遗愿
Because that was the last wish of a dying man.
我会杀了卡莫德
I will kill Commodus.
罗马的命运就交给你了
The fate of Rome I leave to you.
奥利里亚斯信任你
Marcus Aurelius trusted you.
他的女儿信任你
His daughter trusts you.
我都会信任你
I will trust you.
但我们时间紧逼
But we have little time.
给我两天...
Give me two days,
我会买下你的自由
and I will buy your freedom.
而你...
And you,
你要继续生存...
you stay alive,
不然我就会死
or I'll be dead.
我们要走了
Now we must go.
他会在等你 站在斗兽场脚下
He'll be waiting for you. Stand at the foot of the colossus.
他会找到你
He'll find you.
不会成功的
It won't work.
皇帝知道太多了
The Emperor knows too much.
对我来说...
And as for me,
变得太危险了
it's becoming dangerous.
我回来时会付钱给你
You'll be paid on my return.
我向你承诺
I give you my word.
承诺?若你不回来呢?
Your word? What if you don't return?
你记得信任是什么吗  朴森姆?
Do you remember what it was to have trust, Proximo?
信任?
Trust?
我有何资格信任人?
Who am I to trust?
-我会杀死卡莫德 -对我有什么好处?
-I will kill Commodus. -Why would I want that?
他令我富有
He makes me rich.
我知你一诺千金  将军
I know that you are a man of your word, General.
我知你会为荣誉而死
I know that you would die for honor.
你会为罗马而死
You would die for Rome.
你会为纪念组先而死
You would die for the memory of your ancestors.
但我  相反地...
But I, on the other hand,
我是个娱乐观众的人
I'm an entertainer.
守卫!
Guard!
他杀了还你自由的人
He killed the man who set you free.
主人  有禁卫军
Praetorians, master.
停止!
Halt!
你去了哪里?
Where have you been?
我派了人召你
I sent for you.
不要这样  哥哥
Please, brother.
什么事在困扰你?
What's troubling you?
格勒斯是否有了新的情人?
Does Gracchus have a new lover?
我不知道
I don't know.
我以为你跟他见过面
I thought you'd seen him.
他像流感般把所有人感染了
He infects everyone like a putrid fever.
为了罗马帝国的健全 必需令议会流血
For the health of Rome, the Senate must be bled.
而他亦会流血
And he will bleed, too.
很快
Very soon.
但不是今晚
But not tonight.
你记得父亲有次怎样说吗?
Do you remember what our father said once?
一个梦...
"It's a dream,
一个可怕的梦...
"a frightful dream,
"那是生命"
"life is."
你觉得那是真的吗?
Do you think that's true?
我不知道
I don't know.
我觉得是
I think it is.
而我只得你和我分担
And I have only you to share it with.
张开口
Open your mouth.
你知我爱你
You know I love you.
我也爱你
And I love you.
去  出去!
Out. Get out!
动身!
Move!
恭喜你  将军
Congratulations, General.
你有些很有说服力的朋友
You've got very persuasive friends.
我哥哥已拘捕了格勒斯
My brother has had Gracchus arrested.
我们不能再等  今晚一定要走
We daren't wait any longer. We must leave tonight.
朴森姆午夜时会来带你出城门
Proximo will come at midnight and take you to the gate.
你的侍从西塞罗会带着马匹 在那里等你
Your servant, Cicero, will be waiting there with horses.
-全部是你安排的? -是
-You have done all this? -Yes.
你冒太大险了
You risk too much.
我欠了太多
I have much to pay for.
你没有欠人什么
You have nothing to pay for.
你爱你儿子  你为他而坚强
You love your son. You're strong for him.
我厌倦了要坚强
I am tired of being strong.
我哥哥憎恨全世界 尤其是你
My brother hates all the world, and you most of all.
-因为你父亲选了我 -不
-Because your father chose me. -No.
因为我父亲爱你
Because my father loved you.
因为我爱你
And because I loved you.
很久以前
A long time ago.
我那时很不同吗?
Was I very different then?
你多点笑
You laughed more.
我一生都觉得孤独...
I have felt alone all my life,
除了跟你一起时
except with you.
我要走了
I must go.
是的
Yes.
那里
There.
我打中你
And I got you.
这个时候扮士兵?
Isn't it late to be playing legionnaire?
我不是士兵
I'm not a legionnaire.
-不是士兵? -我是斗士
-Not a legionnaire? -I'm a gladiator.
斗士?
A gladiator?
斗士只在竞技场搏斗
Gladiators only fight in the games.
你不宁愿像凯撒大帝般 做个罗马战士?
Wouldrt you rather be a great Roman warrior like Julius Caesar?
我是麦克西马  罗马的救世者!
I'm Maximus, the savior of Rome!
罗马的救世者?
The savior of Rome?
是谁说的?
And who said that?
路西亚斯在哪里?
Where's Lucius?
他跟皇上一起  公主
He's with the Emperor, my lady.
-怎么会 -她的确那样
-She couldn't. -Yes, she did.
她在篮中拿出来...
She took it from a basket,
把它压在胸部 就在心口对上
and pressed it to her breast, right here above her heart.
-它咬了她的胸? -是的
-It bit her in the breast? -Yes.
你知吗  有时那些贵族女士...
You see, Lucius, sometimes royal ladies
为了爱会做些很奇怪的东西
behave very strangely and do very odd things in the name of love.
-我觉得那样很傻 -我也觉得是
-I think it's silly. -So do I.
我也觉得是
So do I.
妹妹  加入我们
Sister, join us.
我在读书给路西亚斯听
I've been reading to dear Lucius.
-我也有读 -是的
-I've been reading, too. -Yes.
他是很聪明的小孩 有天会成为伟大的皇帝
He's a very clever little boy. He'll make a grand emperor one day.
我们之前在读伟大的马克安东尼
We've been reading about the great Mark Antony,
和他的埃及历险
and his adventures in Egypt.
还有那皇后用蛇杀死自己
And the queen killed herself with a snake.
你还未听我们祖先的故事呢
And just wait until you hear what happened to our ancestors.
你乖的话
If you're very good,
明晚我便跟你说 哥狄阿斯皇帝的故事
tomorrow night, I'll tell you the story of Emperor Claudius.
他被最亲近的人...
He was betrayed
出卖了
by those closest to him.
他的亲人
By his own blood.
他们在黑暗角落低声说话...
They whispered in dark corners
晚上很夜出去...
and went out late at night,
在计划密谋
and conspired, and conspired.
但哥狄阿斯皇帝知道他们有阴谋
But the Emperor Claudius knew that they were up to something.
他知道他们是忙碌的小蜜蜂
He knew they were busy little bees.
有一晚他召见其中一个
And one night he sat down with one of them,
他看着她...
and he looked at her,
然后说...
and he said,
告诉我你一直在做什么...
"Tell me what you've been doing,
忙碌的小蜜蜂
"busy little bee.
不然我会宰掉你最亲的人
"Or I shall strike down those dearest to you.
"你会看着我用他们的血来沐浴"
"You shall watch as I bathe in their blood."
那皇帝很伤心
And the Emperor was heartbroken.
从来没人比那小蜜蜂伤害得他更深
The little bee had wounded him more deeply than anyone else could ever have done.
路西亚斯  你估接着发生什么事?
What do you think happened then, Lucius?
我不知道  舅父
I don't know, Uncle.
那小蜜蜂告诉他所有东西
The little bee told him everything.
开闸  皇上有令!
Open, in the name of the Emperor!
朴森姆!
Proximo!
开闸  皇上有令!
Open the gates, in the name of the Emperor!
朴森姆!
Proximo!
开闸!
Open the gates!
朴森姆  开闸
Open the gates, Proximo.
你想死吗  老家伙?
Do you want to die, old man?
拿着
Here.
一切准备好了
Everything is prepared.
看来你赢得自由了
It seems you have won your freedom.
朴森姆  你变成好人有危险吗?
Proximo, are you in danger of becoming a good man?
-祖巴 -与皇帝为敌都要死!
-Juba. -All enemies of the Emperor die!
开闸!
Open the gates!
拉!
Pull!
快!在左边列阵!
Move! Form a column on the left!
我只需片刻 因此你们要好好保护性命
I only need moments, so do not be careless with your lives.
如果你不想参与 回自己的牢房去
If you don't want any part of this, go back to your cells.
我们会在这里等你  麦克西马
We'll wait here for you, Maximus.
-力量与荣耀 -力量与荣耀
-Strength and honor. -Strength and honor.
去吧
Go.
力量与荣耀
Strength and honor.
瞄准  拉弓!
Aim. Arch your bows!
奥利里亚斯914-922
朴森姆
尘与影
Shadows and dust.
麦克西马!
Maximus!
对不起
I'm sorry.
完成了
It's done.
我应怎处置我的外甥?
And what of my nephew?
还有他的母亲?
And what of his mother?
他们是否应跟她爱人同一命运?
Should they share her lover's fate?
还是我应该慈悲?
Or should I be merciful?
慈悲的卡莫德
Commodus the Merciful.
让路西亚斯跟我
Lucius will stay with me now.
如果他母亲...
And if his mother
用令我不快的...
so much as looks at me
眼神看我
in a manner that displeases me,
他会死
he will die.
如她决定高贵地...
If she decides to be noble,
结束自己生命
and takes her own life,
他会死
he will die.
至于你...
And as for you,
你会爱我...
you will love me,
就像我爱你一样
as I have loved you.
你会替我诞下纯血统的继承人
You will provide me with an heir of pure blood,
让卡莫德...
so that Commodus
和他的子孙可统治一千年
and his progeny will rule for 1,000 years.
我不仁慈吗?
Am I not merciful?
我不仁慈吗!
Am I not merciful!
麦克西马!
-Maximus! Maximus! Maximus! -Maximus! Maximus! Maximus!
我是军人  我职责是服从
I'm a soldier. I obey.
没人可以逼你做你不愿意的事
Nothing happens to anyone that he is not fitted by nature to bear.
麦克西马!
Maximus.
他们在叫你
They call for you.
由将军变成奴隶
The general who became a slave.
由奴隶变成斗士
The slave who became a gladiator.
公然反抗皇帝的斗士
The gladiator who defied an emperor.
很引人入胜的故事
A striking story.
现在他们想知道故事的结局
Now the people want to know how the story ends.
只有精彩的死亡才配这故事
Only a famous death will do.
还有什么比...
And what could be more glorious
在斗兽场挑战皇帝更光荣?
than to challenge the Emperor himself in the great arena?
-你会跟我打? -为什么不?
-You would fight me? -Why not?
你以为我害怕吗?
Do you think I'm afraid?
我认为你一生人也在害怕
I think you have been afraid all your life.
不像无敌的麦克西马  没有恐惧?
Unlike Maximus the Invincible, who knows no fear?
我认识一个人曾经说: 死亡对着我们微笑
I knew a man who once said, "Death smiles at us all.
"我们只能也对着它微笑"
"All a man can do is smile back."
我在想...
I wonder,
你那朋友有没有对自己的死微笑?
did your friend smile at his own death?
你要知道
You must know.
他是你父亲
He was your father.
你爱我父亲  我知道...
You loved my father, I know,
但我也是
but so did I.
我们因此是兄弟  不是吗?
That makes us brothers, doesn't it?
为我微笑  兄弟
Smile for me now, brother.
替他着盔甲  遮掩伤口
Strap on his armor. Conceal the wound.
环形阵!
Ring formation!
昆特斯  剑
Quintus, sword.
给我你的剑
Give me your sword.
剑!给我一把剑!
Sword! Give me a sword!
插剑入鞘
Sheathe your swords. Sheathe your swords!
麦克西马
Maximus.
昆特斯
Quintus.
放了我的人
Free my men.
让格勒斯议员复职
Senator Gracchus is to be reinstated.
有一个梦想的罗马
There was a dream that was Rome.
应该会实现
It shall be realized.
那就是奥利里亚斯的愿望
These are the wishes of Marcus Aurelius.
放了囚犯  去!
Free the prisoners. Go!
麦克西马
Maximus.
路西亚斯安全了
Lucius is safe.
去找他们吧
Go to them.
你回到家了
You're home.
罗马值得一个好人牺牲性命吗?
Is Rome won'th one good mars life?
我们一度相信
We believed it once.
让我们再次相信
Make us believe it again.
他是罗马的将士
He was a soldier of Rome.
让我们给他荣耀
Honor him.
谁帮我抬他?
Who will help me carry him?
现在我们自由了
Now we are free.
我会再见到你
I will see you again.
但还未是时候
But not yet.
还未是时候
Not yet.
致我们的好友 奥利华利特